See you guys, welcome to another video, let's learn the common protocols and port numbers.
It is very important for when you are attending any interviews or it's important to understand
the protocols and port numbers, very common protocols and port numbers because we are in
an ethical hacking, we are in the domain of cyber security, so we need to understand the
protocols and port numbers because we are using port numbers in 80% of the time we are using
port numbers to get into the mission to hack the organization, okay.
So if you see what is a protocol, it's a set of rules that how the data can be transmitted
from one place to another, another one source to one destination, there are some rules
behind that, so the protocol is like a rule for a network communication transmitting
from one place to another, we have a lot of protocols like HTTP, HTTP, FTB, SMTB, a lot
of things and a lot of protocols are there but we will see a few common protocols that
was misused and that can be used for an attack and that can be used to take a reverse
connection, okay. So let's first see what is a HTTP, so HTTP stands for a hypertext
transport protocol, so this protocol used for websites, so if you want to do any things
in a web application, so if you want to do some, if you want to contact some servers or
if you want to go to any, if you want to communicate to any servers, this is protocol, we
are using, okay. So if I just browse the Google, so you can see there is a protocol
let's get added, the HTTP is and let I will go to one web server just one web, so now you
can see this website has a HTTP protocol, it's not secure, right. So we all know the
difference between the HTTP and HTTP is, so this protocol is used for web browsers to load
their web pages and we need to communicate to the web servers and we need a result for that,
so this is, this two protocols are used for a web application, okay. So that's why the protocol
used to transfer data over the web, okay. So see this line and in HTTP, we all know
the encryption will be there, so it will be securely transmit the data from one place to
one another, okay. So let's talk about another protocol, it's the FTP file transfer protocol,
let's draw something, so now you have a file server, okay. So in a large organizations,
so the organization have a separate FTP server, file server, okay, file server, inside
the file server, so all the files will be present under the file server, okay maybe the executable
files and whatever files need for resource versions or sales department or IT department
or any cybersecurity department, so every executable files, share points, documents and
everything will be under the file server, so if you need to access any of the files from
the server, you need the FTP, you are going to use the FTP protocol, okay. So FTP protocol
is used for a file transfer from one place to one another, so you are using the FTP to
take the file from here to here, okay. So why the organization have a file server, okay,
because let's see, the organization have an end number of system maybe thousand plus
machines will be there in an organization, so if the, if the network administrator said
the thousand system needs to, the thousand user needs to install the binder.exe from the
internet, so there will be some, miss usually be happened right, so some of them will be downloaded
from the bine website and some of them will be downloaded from the cracked website, so that time
the trojan, the malware will be entered into the machine, so what the organization will do,
organization will create a separate file server for that, so from this file server, okay,
so separate file server for that, instead of the file server, every executable, every
files will be present under this file server, okay. What are the files which will be commonly
used by the users under the organization that will be present under the file server, so only
user can use the FTP protocol to access this files and they can download the files into their
machine, okay, so they can download large number of data from the file servers to their, to their
machine, okay, that's the main purpose of the file transfer protocol, okay, it's an FTP, it will use
the port 21 and the port 820 for a data transfer, okay, so port 21 for command and control and port
20 for data transfer, okay, so let's check the SSK secure shell, so what is the secure shell, it will
give a command prompt, okay, basically it will give a remote command prompt into your system,
let me see that in a practical way, so here you can see it's my Kali machine, so you can install
the Kali machine in the next lab environment, so now let's understand the ports and protocol here,
so I have my Kali machine and this Kali machine have a IP address of 192.168.18.27,
so there is one on application called putty.exe, so if you want to download the putty.exe,
so you can go ahead and it's an open source, you can go ahead and download the putty.exe from
this website, okay, so here you can see download putty and this is the installer, so you can
double click and install that, there is no configuration file filter for that, so once you download
download or the putty will be like this, okay, so here you can see there is a telnet and other
in others you can see the telnet and some protocols are there, and I was using the SFH now,
so I was using the, I can operate my Kali machine in the terminal, okay, even in the terminal,
I can go for I can give Ls and check out the directories are there, but if you see in putty,
so let I will close my minimize my Kali machine first and I will use this putty to
communicate with my Kali machine, okay, I will explore the Kali machine from the putty, okay,
27, so I was communicating with the port 22, basically the SFH port number also 22,
we are using port 22 for a secure shell, so you can see the port number and if I do open,
so this is the Kali machine IP, you all know the Linux machine IP, Kali next machine IP,
so now it was asking for a log in us, I was giving the Kali and I was giving the password as a
Kali, okay, so now you can see I can operate the Kali Linux machine from here, I can switch
user to root even, so now you can see I am in the root and I am giving Ls here, so let me go to
some places like downloads, they will see what are the files are in the downloads, so now you can
see there is a socket.exe and some CV based files are there, so same, let me go to the,
okay, let me explore from here,
so now you can see similar files are present inside my Kali machine, so you can explore,
you can control the Kali machine, you can control the machine from the putty.exe,
so this is the, this will give the command and control, okay, this will open a little command
prompt like that, so Windows, you can say this is a command prompt, it will also give the
similar command prompt like that, you can control the Kali machine from your putty.exe application,
so this is the use of SS cage, SS cage, okay, so in the SS cage we are securing our data in
secure way, if I open a where shark and if I check, let me open the or shark and if I am giving port,
let me filter it with the IP,
so our Kali machine IP will be 27, so you can
okay, let's conclude there is no data, there is no data will be here,
plus some other data, maybe some configuration changes filter, the communication was not logged
into the where server, let I will communicate now using the IR, let's see, got any
of connections,
let's try to filter it now and see whether there is any data communication was there, so
the port was not logged in the where shark, but it will be secure, there is there will be an encryption
will be there, you can't able to see the data what it was sending, okay, it will be used some
cryptography algorithm and it will encrypt the data, okay, so before transmitting, so let's use the,
there's a telnet, there is a protocol called a telnet, telnet is also a similar like a SS cage,
but telnet will not use the encryption, okay, so SS cage will use the encryption for a secure data
transmission, so because you are logging with the username, username and password credentials,
so it will be in a secure format, but if you take the telnet, it will not use the encryption,
so your data could be, your data can be monitored by the attackers and they can shift the data
and they can see what the data you are sending and what the username you are logging, okay,
so it's like ever stopping, okay, so it was the, it was using the port number 23, in SS cage,
it was using the port number 22 and telnet using the port number 23, okay, that's the difference
and there's no encryption will be there in the telnet and SS cage, but it will be
work in a similar way, it will be give a similar command, command and control like this, okay,
let's close the put data, go to the next protocol, so let's understand about the
SMTP, simple mail transfer protocol, so this protocol is used for transferring
mails from one place to another, so if you, if your system, or if your mobile do not have this
protocol, so you can't able to access, you can't able to send any emails to, to your friends
or to anyone, okay, also your emails will not be received, so someone is sending some emails to you,
the emails will not be received in your mobile, okay, so this protocol is completely used for
mail service to sending mail from one place to another and the next protocol we have a DNS,
domain name system, so we have the computer only know the IP addresses, okay, so the computer does
not know, let's explain, go for a DNS, okay, for DNS stands for the domain name system,
in basically the computer does not know the I, the domain names like google.com, okay,
the computer only know the numbers, okay, it only know the numbers, so numbers means the IP address,
right, but it only know the IP address, so you can't able to remember all the IP address for
all the domains, okay, now the, even you can't able to remember the Google IP, I'm sure, and Google
or Microsoft or any IP, there's a lot of websites are there, you are researching about a lot of
websites, so you can't able to remember all the IP addresses, so the Microsoft introduced DNS,
domain name system, this will convert your domain name into the IP address, okay, google.com
into the IP address, okay, so now if you see the command prompt or if I ping google.com,
so this is the IP address of the Google 172.2.17,
so basically the DNS protocol will convert the domain name into the IP address, okay, that's a
purpose of the DNS.exe, and finally we have an one more protocol called the DHCP, dynamic host
configuration protocol, okay, so you may all know when you're connecting your mobile phone or when
you're connecting your computer into the Wi-Fi, so it will automatically give IP address to you,
right, so it will automatically assign one IP address to you, like, IP config, sorry, IP config,
so this is my IP address 160.18.29, this will be given by a DHCP protocol, okay, so dynamic host
configuration protocol, so every machine and every router modem has this protocol, so this is the
hand trick for this protocol, DHCP can could anyone give me an IP, so you are asking the
DHCP server, so basically it will be present in the router, so you are asking the router to get,
could you, could anyone give me an IP, so your router will give some set of IP to you, okay,
just do you want to use this IP, it will give you this 103 IP, then you are sending,
yes, I am really going to use this IP, or you sure, I can use it, okay, finally, the DHCP
app will be sent, okay, so this is like a door-out process, discover, offer, recused, and act,
acknowledge, okay, door-out, discover, offer, recused, and acknowledge, okay, you are discovering,
like, I need an IP, and the server, the DHCP server giving some IP to you, that's offer,
and you are sending a recused, okay, this is enough, okay, this I will use this IP,
like that, okay, so finally, the DHCP will act, okay, use that IP for the data communication,
so this is the entire process of the entire handshake of the DHCP, so now we have completed the
networking section, so this is enough for the scores, for LAN, more things, so LAN cyber security,
so the interview co-stains will become under this OSA model and the protocols and the port numbers,
and this knowledge is enough for jumping to the other session in our course, okay,
so thank you for watching, let's continue in the next section,
so in the next section you are going to understand the lab installations and all, okay,
so thank you, see you, bye-bye.